Guide to the Dennis Wrong Papers MC.262
New York University Archives
Dennis Wrong Papers
1947-2009
New York University Archives
Wrong, Dennis H. (Dennis Hume), 1923-2018
MC.262
17 Linear Feet in 17 record cartons.
Dennis Wrong (1923- ) is a Canadian sociologist and emeritus professor of sociology in the New York University Department of Sociology. As a professor Wrong taught at the University of Nevada at Reno, the University of Toronto, The New School, Brown University, and Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey, but spent the bulk of his academic career at NYU. This collection consists of materials created and collected by Wrong in the course of his personal and professional life, including personal correspondence, outlines for original writings, conference notes, autobiographical essays (including one later published in Authors and Their Lives), and his Ph.D. dissertation from Columbia University. Frequent correspondents include Norman Podhoretz, Irving Howe, Alfred Kazin, David Riesman, Hannah Arendt, and Caroline Purcell, former chair of the NYU Department of Sociology. The collection also contains books and academic journals written or collected by Wrong, many of which have been annotated. The materials document the teaching of sociology at NYU, the department's separation from anthropology, and the larger discussions in the discipline concerning quantitative reasoning and analysis.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials created and collected by Dennis Wrong in the course of his personal and professional life. Materials include personal correspondence, outlines for original writings, conference notes, autobiographical essays (including one later published in Authors and Their Lives), and his PhD dissertation from Columbia University. Frequent correspondents include Norman Podhoretz, Irving Howe, Alfred Kazin, David Riesman, Hannah Arendt, and Caroline Purcell, former chair of the NYU Department of Sociology. The collection also contains books and academic journals written or collected by Wrong, many of which have been annotated. The materials document the teaching of sociology at NYU, the department's separation from anthropology, and the larger discussions in the discipline concerning quantitative reasoning and analysis.
Conditions Governing Access
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Some materials in Box 14 are restricted.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical / Historical
Dennis Wrong (1923- ) is a Canadian sociologist and emeritus professor of sociology in the New York University Department of Sociology. As a professor Wrong taught at the University of Nevada at Reno, the University of Toronto, The New School, Brown University, and Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey, but spent the bulk of his academic career at NYU. Wrong is the author of several books and articles, and has been involved in the editorial boards of numerous publications, including the New York Review of Books, Dissent, Commentary, and Partisan Review. Wrong was at the center of the debates among leading intellectuals from the 1950s-1980s that concerned McCarthyism and the Cold War. He was also a prominent voice during the 1980s-1990s in the discussions surrounding the emergence of the Neoconservatives. The Dennis Wrong Award is given for the best graduate paper of the year by the NYU Department of Sociology.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Terry Wrong in April of 2016. The accession number associated with this gift is 2016.019.
Sociologists -- United States; Sociology.; New York University. Department of Sociology
- Correspondence, circa 1950-2004 (Box 1)
- Academic Journals and Books by Wrong, circa 1950-2004 (Box 2)
- Books, circa 1950-2004 (Box 3, Box 4)
- Books and Correspondence, circa 1950-2004 (Box 5)
- Books, Autobiographical Essays, and Hannah Arendt Correspondence, 1971-2003 (Box 6)
- Books, Correspondence, Calendars, and Journals, 1959-2009 (Box 7)
- Academic Journals, 1950-2004 (Box 8, Box 9)
- Academic Journals, Course Syllabi, and Reprints, 1964-1999 (Box 10)
- Correspondence (Teaching Related), 1959-2000 (Box 11)
- Books, 1966-1995 (Box 12)
- Books and Correspondence, circa 1950-2004 (Box 13)
- Correspondence (including Tenure Recommendations), 1947-1996 (Box 14)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Some materials in Box 14 are restricted.
- Books and Correspondence Related to the Books, circa 1950-2004 (Box 15)
- Correspondence (including Caroline Purcell), circa 1950-2004 (Box 16)
- Correspondence (including George Kennan), circa 1950-2004 (Box 17)